#### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/gideonmaina (LinkedIn) github.com/CodeForAfrica/ (Company)

### Top Skills

Sustainable Urban Planning Public Policy **JavaScript** 

#### Certifications

RESPIRA-AQM Stakeholder Workshop

Electrification of buses and integration in cities' public transport systems

CAMS-Net/AfrigAir Capacity Building

# gideon maina

Electrical and Electronics Engineer by profession | IoT Engineer - sensors.AFRICA #CodeForAfrica | Full Stack Web Developer Hydroponic Farming Technology. #AirQualityMonitoring View projects at gideonmaina.me

Kenya

## Summary

I am in a life-long pursuit to acquire knowledge and put it to good use. It doesn't matter where it comes from as long as I get it. That for me is true wealth. Every day is an opportunity to make my life and the lives of people around me better.

As a lover of science and technology, I pursued a degree in electrical and electronics engineering. I have honed my skills through tinkering with a lot of projects and hands-on experience on an industry level. My experience is largely attributed to working with a number of notable institutions in a multidisciplinary setting. My fascination with electronics and automation persuaded me to venture into programming/software development. The journey was tough but always exciting. I began working with embedded systems as a hobby and developing simple Android apps. Briefly, I shifted careers and became a web developer attaining invaluable skills that intertwine with my professional background.

My technical proficiencies include:

Programming languages: C/C++, Python, JavaScript, PHP, Java-ish Tools: Matlab, KiCad, Proteus, National Instruments, Arduino IDE,

Pycharm, Git, Docker

Databases: SQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB

Frameworks: Vue

I also tried my hand in farming and e-commerce business with varying success. Travelling and exploring new places is my go-to activity when I am unwinding.

Experience

Code For Africa

Senior IoT Engineer

October 2021 - Present (3 years 9 months)

Nairobi

Tasked with overseeing the development of sensors within the sensors.AFRICA team and driving pioneering IoT projects.

Liaise with the tech team to develop, maintain and improve software and development processes:

- 1. Backend and frond-end web-tools architecture
- 2. Review firmware, hardware schematic and PCB designs

Shape the strategies for standardised sampling and measuring standards, equipment protocols, and data management systems.

Improve and optimise the ongoing performance, scalability, and reliability of sensors.AFRICA's software systems to support the growing size of the sensor networks.

Liaise with the internal team and stakeholders to develop strategic decisions involving CfA's partners to achieve actionable insights from the technologies we use.

#### MODERATE LIMITED

2 years 3 months

Electrical Engineer

August 2017 - October 2019 (2 years 3 months)

Nairobi, Kenya

#### Electrical Engineer

August 2017 - August 2018 (1 year 1 month)

Nairobi, Kenya

#### Kenya Power

Intern

May 2016 - August 2016 (4 months)

Nairob

Worked in various substations within Nairobi in the following departments/ sections:

- 1. Operations & Maintenance (O&M)
- 2. Construction
- 3. System Protection

#### 4. Electrical Plant

Powergen Technologies Ltd Engineering Intern June 2015 - September 2015 (4 months)

Nairobi, Kenya

Worked in conjunction with KPLC in the Last-Mile Project in Kibera slums. Duties included:

- 1. Installing prepaid meters to households
- 2. Installing service drops (connecting households to utility lines)
- 3. Maintanance of low voltage networks

Kenya Airports Authority Engineering Intern May 2014 - September 2014 (5 months) Embakasi, Nairobi

Worked with the electrical and mechanical departments of KAA at Jomo Kenyatta International Airport.

Main duties revolved around maintenance and repair of the following systems/ equipment:

- 1. Aviation Ground Lighting (AGL) systems
- 2. Apron Floodlighting
- 3. Streetlighting
- 4. Diesel generators
- 5. Radio telemetry and crash alarm system
- 6. Private Automated Branch Exchange (PABX) system
- 7. VHF radio transceivers
- 8. Public Address (PA) systems

## Education

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology
Bachelor's degree, Electrical and Electronics Engineering · (September 2012 - October 2017)

Miramar International College Hydroponic Farming Technology